Henry Smith Munroe Papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Henry Smith Munroe Papers
1804 - 1934
Connecticut Historical Society
Munroe, Edmund and Henry Smith
Collection consists of personal correspondence between Henry Smith Monroe and his family, and correspondence dealing with Munroe's mining and engineering works, as consultant and as a teacher of mining at universities in the United States and Japan. A significant portion of the correspondence, and its supporting documents, relate to lands and land deals in Tennessee. Also included are numerous maps and plans and diagrams of mine workings, surveying statistics and engineering diagrams. Some material touches on Munroe's role as professor of mining at Columbia University.
6.5 linear feet (13 boxes)
Biographical Chronology
1850 -- Born in Brooklyn, NY
1869 -- E.M. Columbia University
1870-1871 -- Assistant Geologist, Ohio State Geological Survey
1870-1872 -- Assistant Chemist, United States Department of Agriculture
1872-1875 -- Assistant Geologist and Mining Engineer, Geological Survey of Yesso, Japan
1875-1876 -- Professor of geology and Mining, University of Tokio
1877 -- Ph.D., Columbia University
1877-1891 -- Adjunct Professor of Mining, Columbia University
1891-1915 -- Professor of Mining, Columbia University
1897-1899 -- Dean, Faculty of Applied Sciences, Columbia University
1917 -- Consulting Engineer, United States Bureau of Mines
1933, May 4th -- Died at home in Litchfield, Connecticut
Scope and Content
Collection consists of personal correspondence between Henry Smith Monroe and his family, and correspondence dealing with Munroe's mining and engineering works, as consultant and as a teacher of mining at universities in the United States and Japan. A significant portion of the correspondence, and its supporting documents, relate to lands and land deals in Tennessee. Also included are numerous maps and plans and diagrams of mine workings, surveying statistics and engineering diagrams. Some material touches on Munroe role as professor of mining at Columbia University.
Arrangement
Papers are organized into seven series based predominantly on original order and the creator (viz. "collector") of a given series. This is particularly apparent in Series I: Edmund Munroe Correspondence, the latter part of which consists almost exclusively of letters authored and written by Harry Smith Munroe.
Series I: Edmund Munroe Correspondence consists of letters to and from Edmund Munroe, Henry Smith's Father, and from members of his immediate family. Much of the correspondence in this series concerns Edmund's dealing with land agents and with land owners in Tennessee, particularly Samuel Barrell of Knoxville, and the Honourable Felix Grundy of Nashville. From ca. 1869 onward the series consists almost solely of letters authored by Harry Smith Munroe, addressed to his parents, and father in particular.
Series II: Henry Smith Munroe Correspondence consists mixed personal and business correspondence, arranged chronologically. Much of the earlier correspondence concerns land acquisitions and dealings with lawyers, particularly Charles Seymour, and surveyors in Tennessee. Such correspondence and other supporting documents relates closely to that of Edmund Munroe and the Barrell Lands. Later correspondence concerns mining and engineering projects, and his work at the Columbia University as Professor of Mining.
Series III: Articles, Reports and Essays consists of written mining and engineering reports, frequently containing technical diagrams and related evidence.
Series IV: Personal Writings consists of diaries, notebooks, travel accounts, jottings and rough calculations.
Series V: Financial Papers consists of bills and receipts of sale, small account books, indentures and agreements, and insurance papers.
Series VI: Columbia University consists of teaching material(notes for lectures), statements of grades, student reports, notebooks on 'academic politics' and material specifically relating to the Summer School of Mining held annually at the School of mines. General interdepartmental memoranda and correspondence, and formal university proclamations may be found in Series 2: Henry Smith Correspondence under the appropriate year.
Series VII: Barrell Lands consists of undated notes and memoranda concerning the Barrell Lands (lands formerly of Samuel Barrell) in Tennessee. Also contains two volumes, one being a survey of those lands by J. W. Davis, the second being minutes of the Trustees of the Barrell Lands for the years 1886-1888. Series II: Henry Smith Munroe Correspondence contains much material relating to transactions and other dealings in regard of these lands, particularly correspondence with land agents and the law office of Charles Seymour of Knoxville. Additional material on the Barrell lands can also be found in Series I: Correspondence of Edmund Munroe.
Series VIII: St. Lawrence Pyrites Company consists of monthly and annual general balance sheets of the St. Lawrence Pyrite Company. Other financial breakdowns include some external contracts, and analyses of milling and extracting operations.
Series IX: Maps, Plans and Engineering Diagrams consists town maps and builders blueprints, engineering diagrams and other technical drawings and illustrations. Some photographs of mining projects are included in this series. Alongside illustrative material are rough calculations and notes relating to mining works.
Series X: Memorabilia consists of invitations, business cards, menus, and tickets.
Series XI: Whitney Estate consists of deeds, agreements and accounts concerning the estates of Sarah Whitney and George Whitney.
Series XII: Felix Grundy Mining Co. consists of two volumes of minutes of the Grundy Mining Company, TN.
Series divisions are based on original order, folders and volumes being arranged chronologically within each series. Series I: Edmund Munroe Correspondence, from ca. 1869 to onward consists principally of letters written by Edmund's son, Harry. These letters have been preserved in this series, rather than moved to Series II: Harry Smith Munroe Correspondence, in the interest of preserving the integrity of the creator of this series, rather than, necessarily, that of the author.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is open, but additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Munroe, Edmund.; Barrell, Samuel.; Grundy, Felix, 1777-1840.
Subjects
Mining schools and education New York New York.; Mining schools and education Japan Tokyo.; Explosions.
Geographic Names
Yesso (Japan) Surveys.
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed; typescripts; typescripts, signed; maps and sketches of mining workings.
Contents:
- I. Edmund Munroe Correspondence
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; includes grant of land (in Calais, ME) from Edmund Munroe to Theodore Wright and Benjamin Servall., 1804 - 1833 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; principal correspondents, Frederick Smith, and Samuel Barrell to Hon. Felix Grundy (Nashville, TN)., 1834 - 1836 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; principal correspondents, Frederick Smith, and Samuel Barrell to Hon. Felix Grundy (Nashville, TN), concerning land in Tennessee., January - June, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; principal correspondents, Frederick Smith, and Samuel Barrell to Hon. Felix Grundy (Nashville, TN), concerning land in Tennessee., July - December, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; principal correspondents, Frederick Smith, and Samuel Barrell to Hon. Felix Grundy (Nashville, TN), concerning land in Tennessee., 1838 - 1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; concerning land in Tennessee. Correspondence with Hon. Felix Grundy and Samuel Barrell., 1840 - 1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; concerning land in Tennessee. Correspondence with Hon. Felix Grundy and Samuel Barrell., 1845 - 1846 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence, to and from Edmund's mother and sister, Susan., 1847 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence pertaining to the Tennessee land holdings of Samuel Barrell; major correspondent, Thomas Anderson (Boston, MA)., 1848 - 1849 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1851 - 1852 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1853 - 1854 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1855 - 1856 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1857 - 1858 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1859 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1860 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1861 - 1863 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe., 1864 - 1865 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; letters from Harry Smith Munroe while at Columbia's School of Mines, and from Edmund's other children., 1866 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; letters from Harry Smith Munroe while at Columbia's School of Mines, and from Cleveland, Ohio., 1867 - 1869 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe when assistant geologist in Cleveland., 1870 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Personal and family correspondence of Edmund Munroe; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Washington D.C., January - June, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Washington D.C., July - December, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Yesso, Japan., 1872 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Yesso, Japan., 1873 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Yesso, Japan., January - May, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Yesso, Japan., June - December, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Yesso, Japan, and at the University of Tokio [Tokyo]., June - December, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence; letters largely from Harry Smith Munroe while in Yesso, Japan, and at the University of Tokio [Tokyo]., June - December, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- II. Henry Smith Munroe Correspondence
  - Letter book kept while at Yesso, Japan, June 14 - September 26, 1874 (Box 14)
  - Letter book kept while at Yesso and Tokio [Tokyo ]University, Japan., September 26, 1874 - January 29, 1876 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence concerning his work at the University of Tokio [Tokyo], and some letters to his parents; includes a statement of grades for his students., 1876 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, largely from family members, but also concerning his PhD studies at Columbia University., 1877 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence; largely personal, to and from his mother and sister., 1878 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence; largely personal, to and from his mother and sister., January - August, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence; largely personal, to and from his mother and sister. Includes some notes on Samuel Barrell, and letters to Charles Munroe from Charles Seymour, attorney, of Knoxville, TN concerning the Barrell lands and the formation of a company. Includes legal deed of sale of ease portions of the land., September - December, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, largely with and concerning Charles Seymour, regarding lands in Tennessee., 1880 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, largely with and concerning Charles Seymour, regarding lands in Tennessee., 1881 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, largely with and concerning Charles Seymour, regarding lands in Tennessee. Includes some personal and family letters., January - May, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and telegrams with bankers and Charles Seymour concerning land in Tennessee. Letters to his mother touching on Tennessee land., June - December, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and telegrams with bankers and Charles Seymour concerning land in Tennessee., January - May, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence concerning mining and engineering components and requests for admission to the Mining Summer Program at Columbia University., June - December, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letter book., 1884 (Volume 2)
  - Letter book., 1884-1889 (Volume 3)
  - Correspondence, personal and business relating to lands in Tennessee., January - March, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, personal and business relating to lands in Tennessee. Some correspondence with colleagues in Colorado., April - December, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence concerning mining and engineering components and requests for admission to the Mining Summer Program at Columbia University., January - September, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and telegrams concerning land in Tennessee. Also includes copies of deeds and other agreements pertaining to this land., October - December, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence; largely personal, to and from his mother and sister. Includes some notes on Samuel Barrell, and letters to Charles Munroe from Charles Seymour, attorney, of Knoxville, TN concerning the Barrell lands and the formation of a company. Includes legal deed of sale of ease portions of the land., January - April, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and telegrams relating to lands in Tennessee., June - December, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. Includes Deed of the Barrell Lands, and design and cost estimate of a new mining tower., 1887 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. Includes blueprint of the land of R. C. Black., January - July, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and telegrams, some personal letters., August - December, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence; largely professional, to and from engineering journals and associations. Some correspondence relating to lands in Tennessee, principally to and from Charles Seymour., January - June, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents concerning mining and engineering projects. Correspondents include iron mining and railroad companies in New England and Tennessee., August - December, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents concerning mining and engineering projects. Includes drafts of letters to the president of Columbia University., January - May, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence concerning real estate transactions, internal Columbia correspondence, and business with machinists and engineering instrument suppliers., June - December, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence; largely internal Columbia University mail., January - June, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence concerning real estate transactions, internal Columbia correspondence, and business with machinists and engineering instrument suppliers., July - December, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence; letters to his mother., June - December, 1895 - 1901 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence concerning the Whitney's estate, mining operations in Bolivia (Oruro tin and silver mine)., 1892 - 1906 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents concerning mining operations; includes a report on the Allatoona gold mine, Georgia., 1907 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence concerning legal action against Mr. Dresser, and negotiated dealings with the St. Lawrence Pyrite Company. Includes copy of engineering report., January - July, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., August, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., September, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., October, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., November, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., December, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., December, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., December, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., December, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents re. Saint Lawrence Pyrite Co.; Supporting documents include surgeon's accident report and an indenture., April, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co. Includes a comparative statement of the Anna mine., December, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with and concerning St. Lawrence Pyrite Co. Contains several reports on sulphur composition of mine core samples., December, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents re. Saint Lawrence Pyrite Co.; includes a report on dryer installation at Stellaville., July, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents re. proposed work at the Stellaville site., July, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and supporting documents re. proposed work at the Stellaville site., August & September, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms, October, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms; includes sample of Draper's patented self-recording thermometer readout, November, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms; includes promotional material from John Muirhead & Son, Contractors, December, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms (particularly regarding dryers), January, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms; includes plan of the town of Canton., February, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms concerning the Stella and Anna mines., March, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms concerning the Stella and Anna mines; includes copy of an agreement between Charles and Taggert and St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., a general balance report for the St. Lawrence Pyrite Co., and plans of the Stella Mine., April, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms concerning the Stella and Anna mines; includes balance report for Christchurch Women's Auxiliary., April, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms concerning the Stella and Anna mines., June 1910 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with engineering firms concerning the Stella and Anna mines; includes balance annual milling statistics for the Stella mine., August - December, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with engineering and analytical chemistry firms, particularly Floyd J. Metzger. Includes photographs of girder deterioration and new girder plans., 1911 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, largely from within Columbia University concerning the 50th Anniversary of the School of Mines., 1912 - 1914 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, largely from within Columbia University concerning a celebratory dinner for Munroe, and the award to Munroe's son, Robert, of a scholarship to the School of Mines, January - August, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, largely from within Columbia University; considerable correspondence and supporting documents re. the Mining and Metallurgical Society of America and its awards., September - December, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence re. engineering and mining projects, particularly with Lieutenant Colonel O. B. Perry of Camp Mede. Includes sketch plan of Senff Tower at the Mount Tom Reservation, 1916 - 1921 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, drafts of letters and supporting documents, largely with external mining agencies. Includes a progress report on milling methods presented to the American Institute of Mining Engineers., 1922 - 1927 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, drafts of letters and supporting documents. Contains printed matter from the Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, and a block-printed Chinese poster., 1928-1934 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, letter drafts and copies, undated, relating to mining., 1928-1934 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Personal and family correspondence., 1906-1918 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Personal and family correspondence., 1920-1933 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (1)., [187-?] (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (2)., [187-?] (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (3)., [187-?] (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (4)., [187-?] (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (5)., [188-?] (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (6)., [188-?] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: personal and family letters (7)., [188-?] (Box 10, Folder 6)
- III. Articles and Reports
  - Report on the composition of samples from Oruro, Bolivia. Drafts., 1907 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Report on the recent explosion at Grand Central Depot, New York, NY., 1910 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Report on tunneling machines., 1918 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Reports by other authors, often with annotations and commentary. On ventilation at Columbia University; Mill Hill mine, Roxbury; The methods of operation of sulphur ore and copper mine, Clay County, AL; report on the Stella mines., [19--] (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Essay on the determination of pace, and ranging., [186?] (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Central Park Survey: explanation of plane tables, 47-56., [19-?] (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Central Park Survey: explanation of plane tables, 59-484., [19-?] (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Central Park Survey: explanation of plane tables, 59-484., [19-?] (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Central Park Survey: explanation of plane tables, 485-505., [19-?] (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Central Park Survey: explanation of plane tables, 506-535., [19-?] (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Incomplete and non-engineering related reports; includes an essay on Bismark, an essay on the capture of Quebec, and writings on Lincoln County., [18-?] (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Report to Eureka Gold and Copper Manufacturing Co., North Carolina., June 1878 (Box 11, Folder 3a)
- IV. Personal Writings
  - Notes, jottings and rough calculations (1)., [18-?]-[19-?] (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Notes, jottings and rough calculations (2)., [18-?]-[19-?] (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Chinese and Japanese manuscript/block printed papers., [18?] (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Geological Survey of Yesso: Journal of Travel. Includes outline map of "Yê-zo or the Hõ-kai-dõ.", 1873 - 1875 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Travel Journal: Japan, [187-?] (Volume 1)
  - Notes on Geology and metallurgy for a class taught by Professor Newberry., 1867-1868 (Volume 4)
  - Notes on the metallurgy of iron, volume 2., 1868-1869 (Box 14)
  - Engineering Notebook, [Yesso?] Japan, [187-?] (Box 14)
  - Geological Notebook, [Yesso?] Japan, [187-?] (Box 14)
  - Travel account and mining survey notebook, Tennessee and North Carolina., [1878] (Box 14)
  - Notes on practical mining., 1889 (Box 14)
- V. Financial Papers
  - Receipts and bills of sale (1). Includes book of accounts with Grocer E. Landen, New Rochelle, NY and cash account book of his mother, Susan, for the year 1844., 1844-[189-] (Box 11, Folder 8)